The American Pronunciation Guide
Presents ''How to Pronounce Human''
You know, I don't think
we answered yesterday the question...
why human beings live the way they are living.
I don't think we went into it sufficiently deeply.
Did we answer it?
We got to a point...
we never answered that question.
I left here feeling...
I left our discussion...
No, I was thinking about it last night...
I mean, this morning rather...
and it struck me that we hadn't answered it fully.
We went to the question of...
can thought observe itself?
Right, yes.
But I think we ought to answer that question.
But I think that what we said
was on the way to answering it.
I mean...
It's relevant to the answer.
Yes, relevant, but it's not complete.
No, it's not complete.
It doesn't really get hold of that issue...
why do people live the way they do...
and why don't they change?
Or why, knowing this, they don't change?
Yes.
Could we go into that a little bit...
before we go on with...
Well, you know, my immediate answer to that question...
was that they like it...
that it provides...
and we came up against
that and sort of pulled away...
that it provides...
I think it's much deeper than that, don't you?
Because what is involved...
if you economically...
if you...
if one actually transformed...
one's conditioning, one's...
the way one lives...
economically you might find yourself...
in a very difficult position.
Right.
And also it is going against the current.
That's right.
Completely against the current.
Are you saying that it might lead...
to a certain objective insecurity for you?
Objective insecurity, yes.
It's not merely a matter of the imagination.
No, no, actual insecurity.
Yes, you see, because a lot of the things...
we were discussing yesterday...
was some illusion of security or insecurity...
Yes.
and there is some genuine...
Genuine insecurity.
Insecurity.
And also, doesn't it imply...
you have to stand alone?
Yes.
You definitely...
you would be in a new...
I mean, you would be in a totally different position...
because you wouldn't be...
No, it's like completely...
not isolated...
away from the stream.
And that means you have to be alone...
psychologically alone.
And whether human beings can stand that.
Well, certainly this other...
is completely to be together.
That is herd instinct...
which all the totalitarian people use...
and also everything is together.
Be with people.
Don't be alone.
Be like them, be with them, be...
I mean, it's all based on competition in some way.
You know, I'm better than you or you're...
Of course, of course, all the Olympiad...
is all that.
Yes.
Well, it's unclear because in some sense...
we should be together...
but not in that sense, you see.
Of course.
I mean, that society is...
it seems to me is giving us...
some false sense of togetherness...
which is really fragmentation.
Yes, quite right.
But it's called being together.
Quite.
It makes you feel that way.
So would you say the reason...
one of the main reasons...
that human beings don't want...
to radically transform themselves...
is that they are really frightened...
not to belong to a group...
to a herd, to a something definite...
which implies standing completely alone...
and I think from that aloneness...
you can only cooperate...
not the other way around.
Certainly if you...
I mean, empirically...
people don't like to be different...
and that we know.
And empirically they...
You must have seen on the television...
Chinese boys training the Russians...
Right.
All these...
Eastern satellite people...
all of them training, training...
and never alone.
Right, yes.
I once was in...
talked to a FBI man...
he came to see me and he said...
why is it that you walk alone all the time?
Why are you so much alone?
I see you are among the hills...
walking alone and...
Why?
You follow?
He thought that it is very disturbing.
Well, I think even anthropologists find that...
in more primitive peoples...
the sense of belonging to the tribe...
is even stronger.
They feel completely lost...
the entire psychological structure...
depends on being in the tribe.
And I think that is one of the reasons...
why we don't want to...
we are frightened.
After all, cling to the misery...
that you already know...
then come into another kind of misery...
that you don't know.
That's right.
But there is a whole action-reaction schema...
that is by being with others...
You are safe.
You are safe and you are...
I mean there is a...
it even goes further...
there is an action...
I mean it is almost as if you are...
you are in a state of...
it is almost as if you could say...
being with others is the off-shoot...
of always living from...
you are this...
I compare myself with you...
and therefore I am together with you...
sort of as the afterthought.
You know what I mean?
In other words, that is part of the circle.
I was going to say...
even if you leave off comparison...
I think there is something deeper...
in the sense that people feel...
this togetherness...
this sense of belonging to the group...
even if they are not comparing...
they just feel it is safe...
you will be taken care of...
like your mother may have taken care of you...
and that you are in a sort of...
gently support...
that fundamentally it will be all right...
because the group is large...
it is wise...
it knows what to do.
I think there is a feeling like that...
rather deep.
The church may give that feeling.
Yes, you have seen those animal pictures...
they are always in herds.
Except you know the mountain lion...
did you ever read about the lion?
There has been some studies done...
by this fellow, Shaler...
in which he shows that the lion...
there is always in lion groups...
there is always one...
who goes off alone.
Yes, yes.
You read about that?
Yes, I heard about it.
Anyway the cats are not...
No, but the feeling of aloneness...
is much more...
has got a great deal in it.
It is not isolation.
Right, right.
I was asking...
people are seeking that sense...
that from the group you have some support...
from the whole.
Now isn't it possible...
that you are discussing an aloneness...
in which you have a certain security.
You see that people are seeking...
in the whole...
in the group a kind of security...
it seems to me that...
can arise actually only in aloneness.
Yes, that's right.
In aloneness...
there is complete security.
I wonder if we could discuss that...
because it seems there is an illusion there...
that people feel that you should have...
a sense of security.
Quite, quite.
And they are looking for it in the group.
The group being the representative...
of something universal.
Group is not the universal.
It isn't, but that's the way we think of it.
The little child thinks...
the tribe is the whole world.
I mean, a human being...
as he lives this way...
if he transforms himself...
he becomes alone.
He is alone.
Because he does...
I mean, that aloneness is not isolation...
and therefore it is...
it is a form of supreme intelligence.
Yes, but could you go into that a little bit?
A little further about it...
not being isolation, you see.
Because at first when you say alone...
the feeling is that I am here...
entirely apart, right?
It is not apart, no.
That perhaps could be...
What do you think it is...
that a person experiences?
I mean, I think there is one part of it...
that people or all people...
seem to gravitate...
like they have to be together.
They have to be like other people.
What would change this?
That, that is one question.
What would change anybody from that?
And second of all...
why should anybody change from that?
And third of all...
what does such a person experience...
when they are alone?
They experience isolation.
I thought we dealt with that fairly...
thoroughly the other day.
That is, after all...
when one realizes...
the appalling state of the world...
and oneself, the disorder...
the confusion, the misery...
and all the rest of it...
and when one says...
there must be a total change...
a total transformation...
he has already begun to move away...
from all that.
Right.
But here he is altogether...
being together.
No, being together...
what is being together?
What does it really mean?
I mean being in this group.
Yes.
What does it really mean?
Well, being together is different...
from this having to be...
No, be identifying oneself...
with a group and remaining with a group.
What does it mean?
What is involved in it?
That is right.
I think one of the things...
that is involved in it...
is what I said before...
is it sets up this comparison.
No, no, no.
Apart from all that superficiality...
what is involved in it?
The group is me.
I am the group.
Right, right.
Therefore there is really...
it is like co-operating with myself.
Well, I think you could say...
like Descartes said...
I think, therefore I am.
Meaning, I think implies that I am there.
You say, I am in the group...
therefore I am.
You see, that is the sort of...
if I am not in the group...
where am I, you see?
Yes.
In other words, I have no being at all.
That is really the condition...
of the primitive tribe...
for most of the members anyway.
And so there is something deep there...
because I feel that my very existence...
and my being psychologically...
is implied in being first in the group.
Right.
And the group has made me...
you know, I say everything about me...
has come from the group, you see?
And I say I am nothing without the group.
Yes, quite right.
I am the group, in fact.
Right, right.
And therefore if I am out of the group...
everything is collapsing.
You see, that seems to me...
as deeper than the question of competing...
as to who is the chief...
or who is the big shot...
or the...
Right.
That is a secondary affair.
Well, except I wasn't really saying...
that that was important...
so much as I was saying...
that the very action of...
what I am trying to get at...
is some of the moment-to-moment experience...
of being in the group...
which is occupying.
But could I say, you know...
the more striking thing is...
what happens when such a person...
is taken out of the group...
and he feels lost, you see?
In other words, all that stuff...
seems unimportant...
because he doesn't know where he is.
Right, right.
He doesn't know what...
he has no orientation.
To life or to anything.
Right.
And therefore, you know...
that might be the greatest punishment...
that the group could make...
would be to banish him.
Yes, they used to do that.
Yes, oh yes.
Look what is happening in Russia...
when there is a dissent out...
he is a dissent out...
he is banished.
Right, right.
So, it's always been...
Sakharov and all those people...
are against the group.
Right, right.
Because such a banishment...
has sort of robbed him of his being.
It's almost like killing him, you see.
Of course.
I think that's where it is...
that the fear of being alone...
alone is translated...
as being isolated from all this.
From... right.
Well, could we say from the universal?
Yes, from the universal.
You see, it seems to me...
you are implying that...
if you are really alone...
or genuinely alone...
then you are not isolated...
from the universal.
Absolutely not.
On the contrary.
That's what he is saying.
But I mean...
and therefore we have to be free...
of this false universal first.
This false identification...
with the group.
This false identification with the group.
Identification of the group...
as the universal, you see.
Treating the group as if it were...
the universal.
Right.
Support of my being or something.
There is something more to that.
What's being said is...
is that there...
by being...
when that localized identification...
that I am the group...
that me...
that false security is dropped...
then one is opened up...
to the participation in...
in something.
There is no question...
you are the universe.
You are that.
You are.
I felt that I was in a certain town...
you see, and I felt...
that was the whole universe.
Then I heard of another town...
beyond that...
which seemed almost beyond the universe.
It seemed that must be the ultimate limits...
of all reality, you see.
Yes.
So the idea of going beyond that...
would not have occurred to me.
Right.
And I think that's the way...
that's the way the group is treated...
to say...
we know abstractly it's not so...
but in the feeling that you have...
it's like the little child.
Is it therefore?
Is it that human beings love...
or hold on to their own misery...
confusion, all the rest of it...
because they don't know anything else?
The known is safer than the unknown.
Right, right.
And...
Yes, yes.
那
To be alone implies, doesn't it...
to step out of the stream.
Out of the known.
Step out of the stream of this utter confusion, disorder...
sorrow, and despair, hope, travail, all that...
to step out of all that.
And if you want to go much deeper into that...
to be alone implies, doesn't it...
not to carry the burden
of tradition with you at all.
Mm-hm.
I mean tradition being the group.
Group.
Tradition also being knowledge.
Knowledge, but it comes basically from the group.
Knowledge is basically collective.
Collective.
I mean, it's collected by everybody.
So, to be alone implies total freedom.
And when there is that great freedom...
it is the universe.
Could we go into that further?
Because you see, to a person who hasn't seen this...
it doesn't look obvious.
Well, it doesn't look obvious.
I think David is right there...
that to be alone implies total freedom.
To a person, to most people, I think...
and I've tested this out recently...
that the idea, even the deep feeling...
that you are the universe...
that you don't have to do anything...
that seems to be so...
Sir, that's the most dangerous thing.
That's the most dangerous thing to say.
How can you say you are the universe...
when you are...
in total confusion?
When you are unhappy, miserable, anxious...
you follow, jealous, envious...
all that, how can you say you are the universe?
Universe implies total order.
I mean...
Yes, the cosmos in Greek meant order.
Order, cosmos, yes.
Chaos was the opposite, you see.
Yes.
But I...
Now listen...
universe, cosmos means order.
Right.
And chaos is what we...
Chaos is what we live with.
That's right.
How can I think I have universal order in me?
That's the good old trick of the mind...
which says order...
disorder is there...
but inside you there is perfect order, old boy.
And that's an illusion.
It's a concept which thought has put there...
and it gives me a certain hope.
And therefore it's an illusion, it has no reality.
What has actual reality is my confusion.
Right.
My chaos.
And I can imagine, I can project...
a cosmos.
Right.
But that is equally illusory.
So I must start with
the fact of what I am.
Right.
Which is I am in a chaos.
I belong to a group.
Chaos, chaos is the group.
Right.
The political leaders, religious, you follow?
The whole thing is a chaos.
So to move away from that...
into cosmos, which is total order...
means not that I am alone...
there is a total order...
which is not associated with disorder, chaos.
That is alone.
Yes, well, let's go into that.
I suppose several people are doing that...
or in that state.
Doing what?
Moving into cosmos, into order.
Order.
Out of the chaos of society.
That's right.
Now, then, are they all alone?
No, of course.
Now, let me want to get it clear.
You see...
No, they don't feel alone there.
There is no...
there is only order.
There is order.
Why are there different people?
Sir, would you say...
suppose...
no, I can't suppose.
We three are in cosmos.
Yes.
There is only cosmos.
Not you, Dr Bohm, Dr Freilberg and me.
Therefore we are still alone.
Order is alone.
Yes, because I looked up
the word alone in the dictionary...
basically it is all one.
All one, yes, yes.
In other words, there is no fragmentation.
There is no fragmentation.
Therefore there is no tree.
That's marvellous, sir.
But you jumped away there.
That chaos and confusion, that's what we got.
So, as we said, to move away from that,
most people are afraid, which is to have total
order.
Alone, as you point out, all one.
Therefore there is no fragmentation when there is cosmos.
Right.
But most people are in confusion and chaos.
That's all they know.
So, move.
How do you move away from that?
That is the whole question.
That is the question.
Here we are in chaos and confusion.
We are not over there.
No, because you may be frightened of that.
May be frightened of that.
Frightened of an idea of being alone.
How can you be frightened of an idea?
Aren't you frightened of tomorrow, which is an idea?
Okay, so it's an idea.
That's all.
They are frightened of an idea, which they have to...
...an idea, which they have projected, which says,
my God, I am alone, which means I am
nobody to rely on.
Right.
Nobody...
But that's an idea.
Well, let's go slowly, because also there is some...
Yes, this is very important.
...correctness.
We have said that to a
certain extent it is genuinely so.
You are not being supported by society anymore.
All right.
You do have a certain genuine danger, because
you have withdrawn from the web of society.
Yes.
If you are...
Right.
...a Protestant in a Catholic
country, it becomes very difficult.
Well, no, I think we are confused here.
I really do.
Because I think if we've
got confusion, if we've got chaos...
No, not if, it is so.
It is so.
Right.
Okay, I go with you.
Now, we've got chaos and confusion.
That's what we've got.
Now, if you have an idea about being
alone while in chaos and confusion, that's just
another idea, another thought.
Right.
Another part of the chaos.
Yes, that's all.
Is that right?
That's right.
Okay.
Now, that's all we've got is chaos and confusion.
Well, I feel you...
Yes.
...watch the question of language, because you see,
when you use the word all, it closes
things.
You see...
Okay.
All right.
In other words, we were saying yesterday that
language has to be more free in its usage,
you know, than poetic perhaps.
And if you use this word
all, you have to watch it.
All right.
But what I'm saying is that
language is not just a word.
It is a language.
And if you use this word
all, you have to watch it.
All right.
But we have this.
We have chaos.
Okay.
Now, that's what we have.
Now, what is going to...
See, I have an idea.
Let me say what my idea is, that
most people are, let's say, unaware, unwilling, don't
believe in, don't know anything about this all one.
I'm not talking about that.
Cosmos.
Right.
We're not talking about that.
That's right.
We don't have that.
No.
All we got right now is chaos.
Sorry about the word all.
Okay.
We got chaos.
All right.
Chaos.
Now, wait a minute.
Being in chaotic condition, to move away from
that, they have the feeling that they will
be alone.
Right.
In the sense of isolated.
Isolated.
Not the sense of all one.
Right.
That's what I'm getting at.
Yeah.
They will be lonely.
That's right.
Isolated.
Of that they are frightened.
That...
Not frightened in terror.
Yeah.
But not...
Therefore, therefore they say, I'd rather stay where
I am in my little pond rather than
face isolation.
That's right.
They not...
And that may be one of the
reasons that the human beings don't radically change.
That's right.
That's like this primitive tribe.
The man...the worst punishment is to be banished.
You see, you're isolated.
Well, you don't have to go to a primitive tribe.
I see people and talk to people all the time.
Of course.
Patients come to me.
They say, look, Saturday night came.
I couldn't stand to be alone.
I called up 50 people
looking for someone to be with.
I had to join this group.
It's much the same.
I think it comes in
a more simple and pure form.
Right.
People just frankly admit it
and they know that's the case.
Right.
So that may be one of the reasons why...
Who?
One of the reasons why human beings don't change.
Right.
The other is we are so heavily
conditioned to accept things as they are.
I mean, we don't say to
ourselves, why should I live this way?
That's certainly true.
We don't...we are definitely conditioned to
believe this is all it can be.
No.
That's important.
You said that's the explanation.
We are conditioned to believe
this is all that is possible.
You see, this word all is
one of the traps that holds us.
Maybe that's the very fact.
Right.
You see, if you say this is all
that can be, then what can you do?
Nothing.
You see, that's this use of language that...
You see, this way of
using language may be a change.
Quite right, sir.
You have to watch that word.
It's the condition.
But the word all...
That's what he's pointing out.
The word all.
You see, the word...
When you say, this is all I know,
you're saying, well, I'm not going to do it.
You're saying, well, I'm not going to do it.
When you say, this is
all I know, you've already stopped.
Right.
Because what does the word all do?
You see, it closes everything.
It says that this thing
is all of reality, you see.
It's got to be real.
Yes.
And one thing is it
turns an idea into reality, apparently.
It gives that sense of reality to the idea,
because if you say that's all there is, then
it has to be real.
Do you see what I mean?
Right.
Yes, I think that's a very good point.
I mean, that's very much like
the points that we've been making.
Right.
I think that's a very active thinking
that thought is complete, where thought, a thought
becomes reality.
Yes.
Is also, I mean, so then
again, the language itself is the condition.
So shall we say human
beings don't radically transform themselves.
They are frightened of being isolated from the group.
Right.
Banished from the group.
That's one reason.
And also, traditionally, we are so...
I mean, I think that's a very good point.
I think that's a very good point.
We are so conditioned that we would rather
accept things as they are, our misery, our
chaos, our... all the rest of it, and
not say, for God's sake, let me change this.
Right.
Well, we have to get out of this conviction
that the way things are is all that can be,
you see.
Yes, that's right.
You see, religions have pointed this out by saying...
Yes.
...there is another world.
Right.
Aspire to that.
This is a transient world, it doesn't matter.
Live as best as you can in your sorrow,
but give... hand over your sorrow to Jesus or
to Christ or somebody, and you'll
be perfectly happy in the next world.
Right.
So the communists say there is no next
world, but make the best of this world.
Well, I think they would say that...
Yes.
...there is no next world.
There is no next world.
I think that there is happiness in the
future in this world, you see, if you really...
Yes, yes.
Sacrifice your children to your everything for
a future, which is exactly the same thing.
But it seems that it's sort of a transformation of
the same thing, that if we say we have this
society as it is and we want to
give it up, but we invent something similar...
Yes, quite.
...to go to.
We have to invent a society.
Yes.
We have to invent it.
It has to be similar if we are inventing it.
So we really have...
...a system.
Yes, but it seems it's an important point
that it's a subtle way of not being alone.
Quite right.
You mean to go ahead and
make it out of the old ideas.
Yes, to make heaven or the future.
Yes.
So what will make human beings change radically?
I don't know.
I think that there's...
This is such a...
You see, even the idea that you're suggesting
here is that they say it can't be different
or it is all the same.
That is part of the system itself.
Agreed.
Now, wait, wait.
May I ask you a question?
Why don't you change?
What is preventing you?
I would say that it's...
That's a tough question.
Yes.
I suppose the answer would be that...
I don't know how to answer it.
Because you never asked yourself that question.
That's right.
Right?
Not radically.
No.
Well, I mean...
We are asking like this.
I mean, we are asking basic questions.
Right.
I don't really know the answer to the question.
Now, so move away from that, sir.
Is it, as our whole society, all
religion, all culture, is based on thought?
Right.
And thought says, I can't do this.
Therefore, an outside agency is necessary.
An outside agency is necessary to change me.
Right.
With the outside agency is the environment,
the leader, Hitler, this, or Stalin and Mao,
or somebody outside, or God.
God is your own projection of yourself, obviously.
And you believe in God,
you believe in Mao, you believe...
You are still the same.
That's right.
You may identify with the state and so on and
so on, but you are still good old me there,
it operating.
So, is it?
Thought doesn't see its own limit.
And no, realize, it cannot change itself.
Realize it.
Yes.
Well, I think that something more subtle
happens, that thought loses track of something,
and it doesn't see that
it itself is behind all this.
Of course.
We said that.
Yes.
Thought has produced all the scale.
But thought doesn't really see that, you know,
abstractly, but I think, you see, in the bones.
What about the whole business that thought, what thought
does, in fact, is it communicates that through gradual change...
That's all invention of thought.
Yes, but that's where I think the hook is.
No, sir.
Please, just listen.
Sure.
Thought has put this world together.
Right.
Technologically as well as psychologically.
And the technological world is all right.
Leave it alone.
We won't even discuss it.
Right.
To observe.
So, psychologically, thought has built all this
world in me and outside me, the churches,
society, and so on.
And thought, does thought realize it
has made this mess, this chaos?
I would say it doesn't, that it tends
to look on this chaos as independently a chaos.
It is independently existent, you see.
But it is its baby.
It is, but it's very
hard for it to see that.
It doesn't see that.
You see, we were discussing that at
the end of the hour yesterday, really.
Yes, that's what I was...
We're coming back to that.
This question of how thought gives a sense of reality.
And you see, we're saying technology deals
with something that thought made, but it is
actually an independent reality once it's made.
Made, of course, like the table, like those cameras.
A machine, and so on.
Yes.
But, you see, it's not a real thing.
It's not a real thing.
But you could say that thought also
creates a reality which it calls independent, but
isn't, you see.
Now, you see, I thought of a good example.
That is the corporation.
You see...
Yes, yes.
You see, people, they are working for
the corporation, and it makes money, it loses
money, or they strike against the corporation, and so on.
But actually, you could say, where is the...
Yes.
You see, where is the corporation?
You see, it's not in the buildings because...
They are part of it.
Well, anyway, if all the people were
gone, the buildings would be nothing, right?
And if the buildings all burned
down, the corporation could still exist.
It exists.
As long as people think it exists.
Right.
And it pays taxes.
It pays taxes.
The corporation pays taxes, not the individual.
Yes, yes.
So does thought realise, see, aware
that it has created this chaos?
No.
Why not?
But you, sir.
Can't I...
Do you realise it?
I realise that thought...
Not you.
Does thought...
Yes.
You see, I have asked you a different question.
Does thought, which is you...
Right.
...thinking, does your thinking realise
that the chaos it has created?
Yes.
I am not saying I don't think it does.
I, I just don't think it can.
I think it does.
Yes.
I think...
When you say out loud...
Well, I 12.
Do you understand that? We
could call it thinking incorporated.
Thinking incorporated, quite, quite.
And you see, the corporation is supposed to be thinking.
Right? Yes.
So we attribute, we give credit for thought...
to this corporation called me.
That's a good way to look at it.
Thought has created me.
But it also thought has
said that me is not thought...
but a reality independent of thought.
Of course, of course.
You see, like, it treats,
you see, thought treats the corporation...
as if it were there, just
standing like the buildings or the table.
It says it's a reality.
It's not a mirror.
You see, I think it's in this question of reality.
You see, if you say there are certain realities...
which are independent of thought, right?
But if you, there are
certain things which are appearances...
like if you're standing on
a cliff looking at the ocean...
you see all the play of
light, which is not an independent reality...
but it's due to the sky.
The sky, the sea, and
me, you see, all are related.
So it's important to keep clear whether it's a reality...
that arises through this whole...
it's dependent on this whole movement...
or whether it stands self-generated, you know, independent.
And thought is treating me as an independent reality.
Of course.
And thought is saying that it is coming from me.
And therefore it doesn't take credit for what it does.
But I...
to me, thought has created the me.
That's right.
And so the me is not separated from thought.
It is the structure of thought.
Right.
The nature of thought that has made me.
Now, does thought, does your thinking...
or does your thought realise this?
I would say yes and no.
It's like in flashes it does.
No, not in flashes.
You don't see that table in flashes.
It is always there.
I think what actually happens though
is that you see the action...
I wonder, it seems as though to really...
if we could be honest about this...
Yes.
...and completely true about it...
what do we see when we...
when we think about it?
What do we see?
And what happens or what is the actuality...
of thought seeing this creation?
No.
We asked a question yesterday, we stopped there.
Does thought see itself in movement?
Right.
Yes.
The movement has created the me...
created the chaos, created the division...
created the conflict, jealousy, anxiety, fear...
all that.
And this is another question.
That yesterday we said that...
we came to a moment where we said...
thought stops.
No.
That's much later.
Please, just stick to one thing.
Okay. But thought...
what I'm trying to get at is...
what is the actuality of thought seeing itself...
Tell me.
You want me to describe it.
No, I don't want you to describe it.
I'm trying to get at what is my actuality.
What is...
what is the actuality that thought sees?
And as I observe this...
again we're in the language here...
the problem of language...
but it seems that thought sees and forgets.
No, please, I'm asking a very simple question.
Don't complicate it.
Does thought see the chaos it has created?
That's all.
Which means...
is thought aware of itself as a movement?
Not, I am aware of thought as a movement...
which the I has been created by thought.
Right.
So I think the question
which is relevant to that is...
why does thought keep on going?
Why does it sustain itself?
Because as long as it sustains itself...
it does produce something...
like an independent reality...
not an illusion of one.
Why does thought...
Why does thought keep on going?
You see...
What is my relationship to thought?
You are thought.
不得了
There is not a you related to thought.
That's the way the language says there is one.
It says that I am
the entity who produces the thought.
Do you see it? Which is to say...
like say General Motors saying, I am the corporation...
which is producing automobiles, do you see?
Right. But look, look, look, right, you're right.
Can I get it? The question is...
I say to you, what is my relationship to thought?
You say to me, you are thought.
In some way what you say is clear...
but that's still what's coming from me, do you see?
In other words, that's still the way thought is moving...
to say it's my relationship to thought.
That's the point to say that
can this very thought stop right now?
Do you see? Yes.
What is sustaining this whole thing at this very moment...
is the question I was trying to get at.
Yes, that's the question.
In other words, say we have a certain insight...
but something happens to sustain the old process...
nevertheless, right now.
That's right. Right now thought keeps moving.
No, he asked a very... Dr
Bohm asked a very good question...
which we haven't answered.
He said, why does thought move?
When it's irrelevant to you.
Why is it always moving? That's right.
So what is movement?
Movement is time.
Right?
That's too quick.
Movement is time.
Oh, of course.
But I think that this...
Movement is movement.
No, no.
That's movement.
From here to there.
Right. What about that?
From here to there, physically.
From here to London, from here to New York...
and also psychologically...
Right.
From here to there.
I am this, I must be that.
Right, but if I...
a thought is not necessarily all that.
I have...
Thought is the movement.
We are examining movement...
which is thought.
Thought...
Look, if thought stops, there is no movement.
I know you...
I am trying to...
This has to be made very clear.
I think there is a kind
of a step that might help...
What is it?
...to ask myself, you see,
what is it that makes
me go on thinking or talking?
In other words, I often can watch
people and see they are in a hole.
Just because they keep on
talking, if they would stop talking,
the whole problem would vanish.
Right?
I mean, it's just this flow of words that...
So, because what they say then
comes out as if it were reality,
into them.
And then they say, that's my problem, it's real,
and I've got to think some more.
Do you see, I think there
is a kind of a feedback saying...
Suppose I say, well, I've got a problem, I'm suffering.
You've got an I, though.
Yeah, I mean, I think that, do you see?
So, therefore, I have a sense I am real.
I'm thinking of my suffering, but it is
implicit that it is I who is there.
And that the suffering is real because I am real.
Right.
And then comes the next thought,
which is, since that is real,
I must think some more.
Right.
Because if it were, that would be the case.
It feeds on itself.
Yeah, and then one of
the things I must think is,
what is my problem, which is that I am suffering.
In other words, I am compelled to
keep on thinking that thought all the time.
Do you see?
And maintaining myself in existence.
Do you see what I'm driving
at, that there is a feedback?
Which means, as thought is movement,
which is time, if there
is no movement, I am dead.
I am dead.
Yes, if that movement stops, then that sense
that I am there being real must go.
Because that sense that I am
real is the result of thinking.
Do you see? This is extraordinary.
Of course it is.
No, no, no.
Actually, in actuality, not in
theory, one realises thought as movement.
Right.
Right?
There is not I realise thought as a movement.
Thought itself realises it's a movement.
Right.
It is in movement.
And this movement, it creates an image of...
Of me or...
...me who is supposed to be moving.
Yes. Yes.
Right.
Now, when that movement stops, there is no me.
The me is the time, is time.
Right.
Put together by time.
Which is thought.
Right.
So, do you, listening to
this, realise the truth of it?
Not the verbal logical statement, but
the truth of such an amazing thing.
Yes.
Therefore, there is an action entirely different from that.
The action of thought as
movement brings about a fragmentary action.
Yes.
And, yes, there is movement, but two opposite things.
Two complementary reactions.
Two movemental reactions.
Two movemental reactions, contradictory reactions.
When the movement, as thought, comes
to an end, there is total action.
Can you say then that whatever technical
thought comes about, then, is in order?
Of course.
In other words, that it doesn't
mean that thought is eternally, permanently gone?
No.
in order, if the right...
It probably plays.
And it comes about.
I mean, the brain can still do that thing.
So, am I, not am I, a human being,
is he afraid of all this?
Unconsciously, deeply, he must realize the ending of me.
You understand?
And that is really the most frightening thing.
My knowledge, my books, my wife, my...
You follow? The whole thing which thought has put together,
and you are asking me to end all that.
Yes. I mean, can't you
say it's the ending of everything?
It's...
Yes.
Because everything that I know is in there.
Yes, absolutely.
So, you see, really, I am frightened...
A human being is frightened of death.
Not the biological death.
To die now.
Death of this coming to an end.
Right.
And therefore he believes in God, reincarnation,
a dozen other comforting things,
but in actuality, when thought as movement...
when thought realizes itself as a movement,
and sees that movement has created the me,
the divisions, the quarrels, the political...
the whole structure of the chaotic world,
when thought realizes it, it sees
the truth of it and ends.
Therefore it is in cosmos.
Then there is cosmos.
Now, you listen to this, how do you receive it?
Do you want me to...
Receive it.
I offer you something.
Right.
How do you receive it?
This is very important.
Yes.
Thought sees it as a movement.
No, no, how do you receive it?
How does the public, who listens to all this,
see, how am I listening to this?
What is it trying to tell me?
How?
He says, I am not telling you anything.
He says, listen to what I am saying,
and find out for yourself whether...
thought as movement.
In that movement has created all this.
Both the technological world, which is useful,
which is necessary,
and this chaotic world.
Right.
How do you receive, listen to it,
or the public, another who is not here,
listen to it?
Right.
How do you listen to it?
How do you...
What takes place in you when you listen to it?
Panic.
No, no.
Is it?
Yes.
There is a panic about the death.
There is that death, a
sort of fear of the death.
There is a seeing, there is a sense of seeing,
and then there is a fear of that death.
Which means you have listened to it,
you have listened to the words.
The words have awakened the fear,
but not the actuality of the fact.
I wouldn't say that.
I think that's a little unfair.
I am asking you.
They awaken the actuality of the fact,
and then there seems to be a very quick process.
There is an actuality of a fact,
and then there seems to be a silence,
a moment of great clarity that gives way
to a kind of feeling
in the pit of the stomach
where things are dropping out,
and then there is a kind of withholding.
Withholding, right.
I think there is a whole movement there.
So you are describing humanity.
Yes, I am trying, yes.
And I am describing me.
You are the humanity.
You are the viewer, the people who are listening.
Right, that's right.
There is a sense of, what will happen tomorrow?
No, no, no, that's not the point.
What will happen?
That is, I am telling you that's that fear.
No.
If, when thought realises as a movement,
and that movement has created all this chaos,
total chaos, not just Patrick,
but complete disorder,
when it realises that,
what takes place, actually?
You are not frightened.
There is no fear.
And listen to it carefully.
Fear is the idea brought about by an abstraction.
You understand?
You have made a picture of ending
and frightened of that ending.
You are right, you are right, there is stop.
There is no fear.
And then there is…
There is no fear when the actuality takes place.
That's right.
When the actuality takes place, there is silence.
With the fact, there is no fear.
But as soon as the thought comes in.
That's right.
Now, the question is,
when the thought comes in.
That's right.
Now, wait, don't go away.
Don't go away.
When the thought comes in.
I've got three minutes more.
Okay, three minutes.
Go on.
The fact and the actuality, no fear.
Ah, that's it.
That's it.
Right.
But, then the thought comes in.
No.
Then it's no longer a fact.
You can't remain with the fact.
Well, that's the same as
to say you keep on thinking.
That's right.
You keep on moving.
Yes.
Well, I mean, as soon as you bring thought in,
that's not a fact.
That's an imagination or a fantasy
which is felt to be real.
Right.
But it is not so, right?
You can't remain with the fact.
So, we were saying something there.
You have discovered something extraordinary.
Right.
When you are faced with fact, there is no fear.
So, all fear is thought, then, is that it?
Yes.
All...
That's right.
That's a big mouthful.
No.
No, but it's...
All thought is fear.
All thought is sorrow.
Right.
That's the other...
That goes both ways, that all fear
is thought and all thought is fear.
Of course.
And except the kind of thought
that arises with the fact alone.
Right.
I want to interject something right here, if
we've got one second, and that is it seems
to me we have discovered something quite important
right here, and that is at that actual seeing,
then the instant of attention is at its peak.
No.
Something new takes place.
Yes.
Something totally that you have never looked at
or it has never been understood or experienced,
whatever it is.
There's a totally different thing happening.
But isn't it important that we acknowledge this
in our thought, I mean in our language?
Yes.
As we are doing now.
In other words, that if it happened
and we didn't acknowledge it, then we're liable
to fall back.
Of course.
I don't get it.
Well, we have to say not only it happens,
but we have to see it that it happens, and
we have to say that it happens.
Well, then are we just...
are we creating a place to...
To localize there or not?
No.
What he is saying is very simple.
He is saying, do you...
does this fact, actuality take place?
And can you remain with that?
Can thought not move in,
but remain only with that fact?
Sir, it's like saying, can remain totally with sorrow.
Not move away, not say, well, it shouldn't be,
it should be, and how am I to get over
it, how... self-pity and all the rest of it.
Just totally remain with that thing, with the fact.
Then you have an energy which is extraordinary.
Right.
So, can you...
It's time.
But I don't...
But it is time.
It's time.
But now you have to say, can you?
You have to say, can you?
It's time.
We have a lot of time.
Can you?
It's time.